Guide to the Johnson and Campbell Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Johnson and Campbell family papers
1757-1918
1774-1820
GEN MSS 980
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.75
(3 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
The papers contain correspondence, legal documents, maps, and printed material by or relating to Guy Johnson and his experiences as Superintendent of Indian Affairs during the American Revolution, as well as documentation of his efforts regarding claims on his confiscated property in the United States. Series I holds Johnson's papers, which include correspondence with family members and British military officers Guy Carleton and Thomas Gage. Also present are two printed almanacs and two autograph manuscript journals recording Johnson's activities and voyages between Quebec and England, and New York and Quebec. Documents in the papers include several on parchment recording Johnson's services to the crown and his lands in New York, a list of accounts with Joseph Brant, and a manuscript record titled "Return of Services performed by the Indians of Colonel Guy Johnson's Department" which details "the Killed, wounded, etc. & damages done to the Rebels from the beginning of the Year 1780 to the end of 1781." Series II holds material related to Johnson's family in Ireland and Great Britain, in particular records of his son-in-law Colin Campbell and daughters Mary Johnson Campbell and Julia Johnson, documenting their involvement in the settlement of Guy Johnson's estate and their efforts regarding his confiscated property. Correspondence holds letters from banker Thomas Coutts, and several petitions the family submitted to the commissioners for American claims. Also present are personal letters to Colin Campbell from others, including British general Sir William Howe, concerning his military career.
Johnson, Guy, approximately 1740-1788
Campbell family
Johnson family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company (Sotheby's London sale, 2000 July 13, lot 200) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund and the Chandler White and Philena Pennell Smith Acquisitions Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Guy Johnson Papers, 1757-1789. II. Campbell Family Papers, 1780-1918.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence, legal documents, maps, and printed material by or relating to Guy Johnson and his experiences as Superintendent of Indian Affairs during the American Revolution, as well as documentation of his efforts to regain his confiscated property in the United States. Series I holds Johnson's papers, which includes correspondence with family members and British military officers Guy Carleton and Thomas Gage, Also present are two printed almanacs and two autograph manuscript journals recording Johnson's activities and voyages between Quebec and England, and New York and Quebec. A group of documents include several on parchment recording Johnson's services to the crown and his lands in New York, and a manuscript record titled "Return of Services performed by the Indians of Colonel Guy Johnson's Department" which details "the Killed, wounded, etc. & damages done to the Rebels from the beginning of the Year 1780 to the end of 1781." Series II holds material related to Johnson's family in Ireland and Great Britain, in particular records of his son-in-law Colin Campbell and daughters Mary Johnson Campbell and Julia Johnson, documenting their involvement in the settlement of Guy Johnson's estate and their efforts regarding his confiscated property. Correspondence includes letters from banker Thomas Coutts, and several petitions the family submitted to the Commissioners for American Claims. The earliest document in the collection is an autograph manuscript copy of the Patent of Creation awarded to Sir William Johnson (1757) and the latest is a photographic reproduction (1918) of a 1772 manuscript survey of Johnson's lands in New York; the original manuscript map, drawn by William Johnson's surveyor Robert Picken, is also in the collection.
Guy Johnson (approximately 1740-1788)
Guy Johnson was born in Ireland, and arrived in the Province of New York in 1756 to became a secretary to his uncle, Sir William Johnson, the British Superintendent of Indian Affairs of the northern colonies. Johnson succeeded his uncle as superintendent in 1774, and also served as a colonel in the Tryon County (New York) militia and a member of the provincial New York Assembly. In 1763 Guy Johnson married his cousin Mary ("Polly") Johnson (died 1775), the daughter of Sir William Johnson; the couple had five daughters, two of whom, Mary and Julia, lived to adulthood. Johnson resigned his superintendency in 1782 and returned to England to seek restitution of his New York property that had been confiscated by the United States government. He died in London on March 5, 1788.
Colonial administrators -- Great Britain; Indians of North America -- Government relations -- To 1789; Mohawk Indians -- Government relations -- To 1789; Mohawk Indians -- History -- Sources; Legal documents -- England -- 18th century; Legal documents -- United States -- 18th century; Maps (documents) -- United States -- 18th century; Vellum (parchment) -- England -- 18th century; Brant, Joseph, 1742-1807; Campbell, Colin, 1754-1814; Campbell family; Campbell, Mary Johnson, 1764-1832; Claus, Daniel, 1727-1787; Coutts, Thomas, 1735-1822; Dorchester, Guy Carleton, Baron, 1724-1808; Gage, Thomas, 1721-1787; Howe, William Howe, Viscount, 1729-1814; Johnson family; Johnson, Guy, approximately 1740-1788; Johnson, William, 1715-1774; Picken, Robert, (Surveyor); Great Britain. Commission Appointed to Enquire into the Losses of American Loyalists, 1783-1789; Six Nations
- Guy Johnson Papers, 1757-1789; Series I; 0.54; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Journals, Documents, and Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters between Guy Johnson and his daughter and son-in-law Mary and Colin Campbell, daughter Julia Johnson, brother-in-law Daniel Claus, brother-in-law (and cousin) John Johnson, and uncle (and father-in-law) William Johnson. Also present are four journals and almanacs documenting Johnson's activities, including voyages between Quebec and England, and New York and Quebec, and petitions and other papers related to Johnson's career, remuneration, and claims on his property in the United States. Other Papers holds documents seemingly unrelated to Johnson.
  - Correspondence
    - Blackburn, John
      - Letters, 1774-1777 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Invoices and accounts, 1784-1786 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Account of Guy Johnson's real estate left in Blackburn's hands, 1776 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Campbell, Colin, 1786-1788 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Campbell, Mary Johnson, 1782, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Carleton, Guy, 1775 Jun 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Claus, Daniel, 1779 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - DePeyster, A. S., 1774 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Forsythe, George, 1782 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gage, Thomas, 1774 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Johnson, John, 1773-1779 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Johnson, William, 1773 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Taylor, William, 1783 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Journals
    - The New-York Pocket Almanac for the Year 1773, by Thomas Moore (New York: Hugh Gaine, 1772) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      General note
      Annotated by Johnson with diary entries, including the building of his house, Guy Park
    - Mills and Hicks's British and American Register, with an Almanack for the Year 1779 (New York: 1778) (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Annotated by Johnson and others with family births and deaths
    - Journal of voyages from New York to Halifax and Halifax to Quebec, 1778-1779 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Journal of a voyage from Quebec to England, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Documents
    - Manuscript copy of Patent of Creation to Sir William Johnson...dated 1755 Nov 27, 1757 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
      Inscribed: "This Patent came out in the Lynn Man of War Feby 1756 on board of which came GJ"
    - Articles of agreement regarding property along the St. John's River, Nova Scotia (printed), circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper clippings and a two-shilling note (Philadelphia, 1769), 1762-1776 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Description of the Harbour and River of St. John's, in Nova-Scotia..., 1768 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Map of the Part of the Patent of Kayadarosseras..." surveyed by Robert Picken, 1772 (Box 4 (Broadside), Folder 23)
      Manuscript map includes Guy Johnson's 2,100 acres and Guy Park on the Mohawk River, New York
    - Indenture of Timothy Connolly (servant) from Francis Wade to Guy Johnson, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Will of Sir William Johnson (and transcript), 1774, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Agreement regarding Abraham Barclay's debt to Guy Johnson, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Indenture between Guy Johnson and Francis Child, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Land-lease agreements between Guy Johnson, Francis Child, and James Downes, 1775 (Box 5 (Broadside), Folder 29)
      Four vellum parchment documents
    - Indentures and other legal documents between Guy Johnson and Francis Child, and James Downes, 1775-1776 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 30)
    - Record of Joseph Brant's accounts, 1775-1779 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Draft of a will of Guy Johnson, 1776 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Certificate for John Montour, chief warrior, attesting to his assistance to the military, 1780 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Return of Services performed by the Indians of Colonel Guy Johnson's Department..., 1781 (Box 6 (Broadside), Folder 34)
      Detailing "the Killed, wounded, etc. & damages done to the Rebels from the beginning of the Year 1780 to the end of 1781"
    - The Case and Claim of the American Loyalists Impartially Stated and Considered (London, 1783) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - The Following Description, with the extracts of letters patent, and proceedings of committees for dividing and settling the townships of Gage, Burton, Conway, Sunbury, and other tracts on St. Johns river... ([Montreal? Fleury Mesplet?, 1783) (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Two copies, one annotated
    - Letter to John Parr, governor of Nova Scotia, 1783 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Inventory of clothing belonging to Guy Johnson in Montreal, 1783 Jul (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Inventory of clothing, bedding, silver, and arms belonging to Guy Johnson, 1784 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Petition of Guy Johnson to the commissioners, with draft and copy, 1784 Mar 23 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 40)
    - Estimate of the Estate Real and Personal of Guy Johnson...in the Province of New York in 1775, 1784 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 41)
      Submitted to the American loyalists claims commissioners March 23, 1784; two copies and a draft
    - Copy of testimonial by Thomas Gage on Johnson's behalf, 1785 Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Record of advertisements of sales of some of Guy Johnson's lands in Montgomery County, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Invoice and receipt of payment from Michael Morris, M.D., 1787 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Case of Guy Johnson as Superintendent of the Indian Nations, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Roll of Foreign Accounts, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Record of salaries, contingencies and other incidental expenses paid by the government to Johnson in his service as Superintendent of Indian Affairs in the Northern District of North America
    - Court summons, Montreal, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Other Papers
    Contains documents not identified with Guy Johnson.
    - Passport and safe conduct issued by Louis XV allowing Mr. Friend and household to travel from France to England, 1772 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 49)
    - Commission appointing Louis Perrault as surveyor of lands for the province of Quebec, 1789 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 50)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1781 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 51)
    - Invitation to the funeral of John, Count O'Rourke, in London, undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 52)
- Campbell Family Papers, 1780-1918; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series II holds material related to Johnson's family in Ireland and Great Britain, in particular records of his son-in-law Colin Campbell and daughters Mary Johnson Campbell and Julia Johnson, documenting their involvement in the settlement of Guy Johnson's estate and their claims against his confiscated property. Correspondence includes letters from banker Thomas Coutts, and several petitions the family submitted to the Commissioners for American Claims. Also present are personal letters to Colin Campbell from others, including the British general Sir William Howe, concerning his military career.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letter from William Howe to Colin Campbell, 1780 Jul 6 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Letters from Joseph Chew to Colin Campbell, 1788-1792 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - State of the late Col. Johnson's account with Phin & Ellice, 1788 Mar 27 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Letter from Colin Campbell to John Johnson, 1788 Apr 3 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Power of attorney for Mary Campbell to her husband Colin Campbell, 1788 Jun 21 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Letter from Colin Campbell to John Campbell, 1788 Jun 17 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence, general, 1791-1857, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Petition of Colin Campbell to the Lords of the Treasury, 1792 Oct 23 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Letters from Thomas Coutts to Colin Campbell, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    Regarding Mary Campbell's attempt to retrieve papers written by her father
  - Letters from John Campbell, one with extract of letter from Patrick Langan, Montreal, 1794, 1801 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 62)
  - Invoice from Mr. Ainslie to Colin Campbell, 1795 Aug 24 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Letter from John Johnson to Colin Campbell, 1803 Feb 21 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Letter from Robert Mackenzie to Colin Campbell, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Copy of Lord Rawdon's certificate relative to the accounts of the late Guy Johnson, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Notes regarding grants of land in Canada to Guy Johnson's heirs and American claims, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Military survey of Captain Egerton's Company, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Estimate on the estate of Colonel Guy Johnson, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Petitions of Mary Johnson Campbell to the Lords of the Treasury, 1815, 1820, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Maps of North America, 1832 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 71)
    Index map of North America and sheet VI from an SDUK atlas
  - Petitions of Julia Johnson to the Lords of the Treasury, 1837, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Johnson family genealogy notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Diary and almanac, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous notes and wax seal, 1876, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - David Ross McCord letter to Guy Campbell, 1916 Oct 23 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Photographic facsimile "Map of the Part of the Patent of Kayadarosseras..." surveyed by Robert Picken; photograph by Jones & Sons, mounted on canvas, 1918 Sep